Finding Aid for the Holden Bovie Schermerhorn Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Holden Bovie Schermerhorn Collection
1919-1931
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0610
.06 linear_feet
Biography/History
Holden Bovie Schermerhorn (1868-1935) was born in Massachusetts. He held PH.B, and LL.B degrees from the University of Pennsylvania, and a LL.M from Temple University of Philadelphia. In 1916, he came to Vanderbilt University as a Professor of Law and with the exception of two years he remained at Vanderbilt in that capacity until his death. And, from 1925-1935 he served as Secretary of the Law School.
From 1918-1920 he was with the Paris branch of Coudert Brothers, one of the largest law firms in the world, with headquarters in New York. While in Paris both during and after the war, he dealt with the many problems of private international law.
Professor Schermerhorn had many interests. He was proficient in art, music, acting, and wrote many articles for journals, and was the author of several books on Torts Law and the Tennessee Parthenon. Although he never took art lessons he was a good artist. Most of his sketches were done in pencil, and the subjects being old buildings and streets in Paris, and later sketches of Vanderbilt University’s College Hall, done in pencil on ordinary photograph mount.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains 6 items: an address, three drawings, and two handwritten manuscripts.
- Address
  - An American Lawyer in the Paris Courts, by H. B. Schermerhorn, Proceeding of the Forty-second Annual Session of the Bar Association of Tennessee, n.d.
- Drawings
  - Paris Bridge, June 18, 1919
  - College Hall, Vanderbilt University, October 1922
  - Reprinted in Campus Portraits in, 1938
  - Bedroom, December 1931
- Manuscripts
  - Among The Brahmins and Pariahs, by J. A. Santer. Translated from the German By Bernard Miall. Reviewed by H. B. Schermerhorn in the Nashville Tennessean in, 1924.
  - Some of the World’s Great Pictures, by H. B. Schermerhorn, n.d.